<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:cc="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/rss/creativeCommonsRssModule.html">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Stories by Linuka Arambawela on Medium]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Stories by Linuka Arambawela on Medium]]></description>
        <link>https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela?source=rss-1e74636a6ac6------2</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/fit/c/150/150/0*tR1cpqOzTBhlNI3u</url>
            <title>Stories by Linuka Arambawela on Medium</title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela?source=rss-1e74636a6ac6------2</link>
        </image>
        <generator>Medium</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:34:38 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[yourfriends@medium.com]]></webMaster>
        <atom:link href="http://medium.superfeedr.com" rel="hub"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloud Computing 101: Introduction to Azure]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela/cloud-computing-101-introduction-to-azure-58be800ae16b?source=rss-1e74636a6ac6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/58be800ae16b</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[cloud-services]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[cloud]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[azure]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[cloud-computing]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[serverless]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Linuka Arambawela]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 05:51:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2024-08-23T11:02:39.453Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*BRKubSEGLN-2bMVLYoqKIA.png" /></figure><h3>What is Cloud Computing?</h3><p>Cloud computing is a revolutionary approach to accessing and managing IT resources, offering computing services such as servers, storage, databases, networking, and software over the internet. By leveraging the cloud, businesses can innovate faster, utilize flexible resources, and achieve significant cost savings. Instead of owning and maintaining physical infrastructure, you pay only for the services you use, enabling more efficient operations and scalability as your business grows.</p><h3>Benefits of Cloud Computing</h3><h4>1. Cost Efficiency</h4><p>Cloud computing eliminates the need for significant upfront investments in hardware and software. By moving to the cloud, businesses can avoid the capital expense of setting up and maintaining on-premises data centers, resulting in optimized IT costs.</p><h4>2. Speed and Agility</h4><p>Cloud services are typically available on-demand, allowing businesses to provision vast amounts of resources in minutes. This flexibility reduces the pressure of capacity planning and enables quicker adaptation to changing business needs.</p><h4>3. Global Scale</h4><p>The cloud allows you to scale resources elastically, delivering the right amount of IT resources when and where they are needed. This global reach ensures optimal performance and availability, regardless of your location.</p><h4>4. Enhanced Productivity</h4><p>Cloud computing minimizes the time spent on managing IT infrastructure. By automating many tasks, such as hardware setup and software updates, IT teams can focus on more strategic initiatives</p><h4>5. Improved Performance</h4><p>Cloud providers operate a global network of data centers equipped with the latest hardware, ensuring fast and reliable service. This setup reduces network latency and benefits from economies of scale.</p><h4>6. Reliability and Security</h4><p>Cloud computing offers robust solutions for data backup, disaster recovery, and business continuity. With data mirrored across multiple sites, the cloud ensures higher reliability. Leading cloud providers also implement strict security measures to protect your data and infrastructure from potential threats.</p><h3>Types of Cloud Computing</h3><h4>Public Cloud</h4><p>In a public cloud, services are owned and operated by third-party providers like Microsoft Azure. The infrastructure is shared across multiple organizations, offering scalability and cost-effectiveness.</p><h4>Private Cloud</h4><p>A private cloud is dedicated to a single organization, providing greater control over resources and security. It can be hosted on-premises or by a third-party provider.</p><h4>Hybrid Cloud</h4><p>Hybrid cloud combines public and private clouds, allowing data and applications to be shared between them. This model offers flexibility, optimized infrastructure, and better security.</p><h3>Cloud Service Models</h3><h4>Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)</h4><p>IaaS provides virtualized computing resources over the internet. It’s the most basic cloud service, allowing businesses to rent servers, storage, and networking on a pay-as-you-go basis.</p><h4>Platform as a Service (PaaS)</h4><p>PaaS offers a platform for developing, testing, and deploying applications. It removes the need to manage underlying infrastructure, enabling developers to focus on coding and innovation.</p><h4>Software as a Service (SaaS)</h4><p>SaaS delivers software applications over the internet, usually on a subscription basis. The cloud provider handles the management of the application, including updates and security.</p><h4>Serverless Computing</h4><p>Serverless computing focuses on building applications without worrying about server management. The cloud provider automatically allocates resources as needed, enabling highly scalable and event-driven applications.</p><h3>Real-World Uses of Cloud Computing</h3><p>Cloud computing is deeply integrated into our daily lives and business operations. Here are some common applications:</p><p><strong>Cloud-Native Applications</strong>: Build and deploy scalable web, mobile, and API applications quickly using cloud-native technologies.</p><p><strong>Data Storage and Backup</strong>: Securely store and recover data from any location with cloud-based storage solutions.</p><p><strong>Streaming Services</strong>: Stream high-definition video and audio content to a global audience on any device.</p><p><strong>Software Delivery: </strong>Distribute the latest software versions to users on demand through SaaS models.</p><p><strong>Data Analytics:</strong> Analyze large datasets in the cloud using AI and machine learning tools to gain valuable insights.</p><h3>Getting Started with Microsoft Azure</h3><p>Microsoft Azure is a leading cloud platform offering a comprehensive range of services for businesses of all sizes. Azure supports all cloud models (public, private, and hybrid) and provides extensive IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS offerings. With Azure, you can easily deploy and manage applications, leverage advanced analytics, and integrate AI into your business processes.</p><p>Azure stands out with its strong global presence, robust security measures, and seamless integration with other Microsoft products. Whether you’re a startup or a large enterprise, Azure provides the tools you need to build, deploy, and manage applications efficiently.</p><h4>Learn More About Azure and Cloud:</h4><ul><li>Cloud Computing: <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/training/modules/describe-cloud-compute?wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>Click Here</strong></a></li><li>Cloud service types: <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/training/modules/describe-cloud-service-types?wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>Click Here</strong></a></li><li>Benefits of using cloud services: <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/training/modules/describe-benefits-use-cloud-services?wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>Click Here</strong></a></li><li>Microsoft Azure Fundementals: <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/courses/az-900t00?wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>Click Here</strong></a></li></ul><p>Ready to explore cloud computing? Get started with a <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/pricing/purchase-options/azure-account?icid=azurefreeaccount&amp;wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>free Azure account</strong></a><strong> </strong>or try <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/free/students?wt.mc_id=studentamb_361742"><strong>Azure for Students</strong></a> with $100 Azure credits.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Cloud computing is transforming the way businesses operate, offering unparalleled flexibility, scalability, and cost savings. Whether you’re looking to deploy new applications, store and analyze data, or enhance your business’s performance, the cloud provides a powerful foundation to achieve your goals. With platforms like Microsoft Azure, you can harness the full potential of the cloud to drive innovation and growth.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=58be800ae16b" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[APIs 101: Introduction to Postman]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela/apis-101-introduction-to-postman-b66ef21d32d5?source=rss-1e74636a6ac6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/b66ef21d32d5</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[application]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[ai]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[postman]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[api]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Linuka Arambawela]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 09:16:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2024-06-13T09:16:54.787Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/906/1*2T3FP4bnMY0-jX7bnPSkCg.png" /></figure><h3><strong>Unveiling the Secret Ingredient of Modern Apps</strong></h3><p>Have you ever wondered how different apps on your phone or computer work together seamlessly? The magic behind this collaboration lies in <strong>APIs (Application Programming Interfaces)</strong>. APIs act as messengers, allowing applications to talk to each other and share data effortlessly.<br>Think of an API as a waiter in a restaurant. You (the user) give your order (request) to the waiter (API), who then tells the kitchen (server) what you want. The kitchen prepares your food (data) and the waiter delivers it back to you.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/628/1*XvPSwm9eTlsWdI4m_SJJeg.png" /><figcaption>( postman)</figcaption></figure><h3><strong>Why APIs Matter</strong></h3><p>APIs are crucial because they:<br>1.<strong>Enable Integration</strong>: They allow different software systems to work together.<br>2.<strong>Enhance Functionality</strong>: Developers can leverage existing functionalities without building from scratch.<br>3.<strong>Drive Efficiency</strong>:Automate processes and reduce redundancy.</p><h3><strong>How APIs Work</strong></h3><p>APIs operate through requests and responses. A client application sends a request to the server, specifying the desired resource or action. The server processes the request, retrieves or manipulates the necessary data, and sends back a response, typically in JSON or XML format. This interaction is facilitated by HTTP methods like GET, POST, PUT, and DELETE, enabling seamless data exchange and functionality integration.</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2F-0MmWEYR2a8%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3D-0MmWEYR2a8&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2F-0MmWEYR2a8%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/4a73d37484c24a4c065f600773c677c3/href">https://medium.com/media/4a73d37484c24a4c065f600773c677c3/href</a></iframe><h3><strong>Types of APIs</strong></h3><p>1. <strong>REST</strong> <strong>(Representational State Transfer</strong>): Uses standard HTTP methods (GET, POST, PUT, DELETE). It’s stateless, scalable, and easy to use.<br>2. <strong>SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol)</strong>: Protocol-based and uses XML. It’s highly secure and reliable.<br>3. <strong>GraphQL: </strong>Allows clients to request exactly what they need. It’s flexible and efficient.</p><h3><strong>Building Your First API: A Step-by-Step Guide</strong></h3><p>To start building an API:<br>1. <strong>Choose Your API Type</strong>: Decide between REST, SOAP, or GraphQL.<br>2. <strong>Design Endpoints:</strong> Define the routes (URLs) your API will respond to.<br>3. <strong>Set Up a Server:</strong> Use frameworks like Express.js (Node.js) or Flask (Python).<br>4. <strong>Implement CRUD Operations:</strong> Create, Read, Update, Delete.<br>5. <strong>Test Test Test:</strong> Use tools like Postman to ensure your API works as expected.</p><h3><strong>Best Practices for API Development</strong></h3><p>1<strong>. Documentation</strong>: Clearly document your API for users.<br>2. <strong>Versioning</strong>: Manage changes without disrupting users.<br>3. <strong>Security</strong>: Implement authentication and encryption.<br>4. <strong>Rate Limiting</strong>: Prevent abuse by limiting the number of requests.</p><h3><strong>Postman: Your API Development Powerhouse</strong></h3><p>Postman is a powerful tool for developing and testing APIs. It provides a user-friendly interface to make HTTP requests, inspect responses, and automate testing. With features like collections, environments, and mock servers, Postman simplifies the API development workflow, making it easier to design, debug, and document APIs.</p><h3><strong>Real-World Applications</strong></h3><p>APIs are everywhere. They power social media integrations, payment gateways, weather data, and much more. For instance, when you log in to a website using your Google account, you’re using an API.</p><p><strong>Unlocking the Power of AI with APIs</strong></p><p>The world of AI is no exception to the power of APIs. Here’s how GPT-3 and Gemini APIs are making waves:</p><ul><li><strong>GPT-3 APIs:</strong> OpenAI offers GPT-3 APIs, allowing developers to integrate powerful text-generation and processing capabilities into their applications. This can be used for tasks like creating marketing copy, generating different creative text formats, or building chatbots with advanced conversational abilities.</li><li><strong>Gemini APIs:</strong> Google’s Gemini APIs provide access to their latest AI models, including multimodal capabilities. This means developers can create applications that work with text, audio, video, and code, opening doors for innovative solutions like generating video descriptions or creating interactive AI experiences.</li></ul><h3><strong>The Final Takeaway</strong></h3><p>APIs are a critical skill for any developer. They unlock the power of integration, enhance functionality, and streamline processes. From building your first API to mastering advanced concepts, the journey is challenging but rewarding. Dive in, experiment, and explore the endless possibilities that APIs offer.</p><p><strong>Want to Deep Dive? </strong>For more detailed information and examples, you can explore the postman documentations [<a href="https://www.postman.com/what-is-an-api/">here</a>].</p><p><em>Postman Student Expert</em></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=b66ef21d32d5" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Beyond HTTP: Leveraging WebSockets for Real-Time Communication]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@linukaarambawela/beyond-http-leveraging-websockets-for-real-time-communication-05e5c4661faa?source=rss-1e74636a6ac6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/05e5c4661faa</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[real-time-communication]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[beyond-http]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[realtime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[websocket]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[http-vs-websocket]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Linuka Arambawela]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 06:30:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2024-05-13T06:30:13.472Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*PTEWTu4gqG9vFwfZcV90FQ.png" /></figure><p>WebSockets are a powerful technology that enables real-time, two-way communication between a web browser and a server. Unlike traditional HTTP requests, which are one-way interactions, WebSockets establish a persistent connection, allowing for continuous data exchange without the need for constant page refreshes. This opens doors for a new level of interactivity and responsiveness in web applications.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/828/1*LIVztBZTW9hgzC2L1sRQkg.png" /></figure><h3><strong>Key Features of WebSockets:</strong></h3><ul><li><strong>Two-way communication:</strong> Data can flow in both directions simultaneously, between the browser and the server. This eliminates the limitations of HTTP’s request-response cycle.</li><li><strong>Full-duplex communication:</strong> Both parties can send and receive messages at the same time, enabling real-time interactions like chat applications or collaborative editing tools.</li><li><strong>Persistent connection:</strong> WebSockets establish a long-lived connection that remains open until it’s explicitly closed. This eliminates the overhead of repeatedly opening and closing new connections for each data exchange.</li><li><strong>Lower latency:</strong> The persistent connection and efficient data transfer protocol of WebSockets result in lower latency compared to HTTP, making applications feel more responsive.</li></ul><h3><strong>Advantages of WebSockets:</strong></h3><ul><li><strong>Real-time updates:</strong> WebSockets enable applications to display updates and changes instantly, without requiring users to refresh the page. This is ideal for live dashboards, stock tickers, chat applications, and more.</li><li><strong>Reduced server load:</strong> By eliminating the need for frequent HTTP requests, WebSockets can significantly reduce server load, especially for applications that require frequent data updates.</li><li><strong>Improved user experience:</strong> The real-time nature of WebSockets leads to a more seamless and responsive user experience, where data feels constantly in sync.</li></ul><h3><strong>Disadvantages of WebSockets:</strong></h3><ul><li><strong>Increased complexity:</strong> Implementing WebSockets requires additional code and considerations compared to traditional HTTP requests.</li><li><strong>Browser compatibility:</strong> While widely supported, some older browsers may not have full WebSocket functionality.</li><li><strong>Security concerns:</strong> As WebSockets establish a long-lived connection, proper security measures are crucial to prevent unauthorized access or data breaches.</li></ul><h3><strong>How WebSockets Work:</strong></h3><p>The process of establishing a WebSocket connection involves a handshake between the browser and the server. Here’s a simplified breakdown:</p><ol><li><strong>Handshake initiation:</strong> The browser initiates the connection by sending an HTTP request containing specific headers that indicate WebSocket support.</li><li><strong>Server response:</strong> The server verifies the request and, if successful, sends a response with its own WebSocket headers, establishing the connection.</li><li><strong>Data exchange:</strong> Once the connection is established, data can be exchanged in both directions using a lightweight messaging protocol. Messages are typically sent in text format (JSON) for easier processing by both parties.</li><li><strong>Connection closure:</strong> The connection can be closed by either the browser or the server by sending a closing message.</li></ol><h3><strong>WebSockets vs. HTTP:</strong></h3><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/770/1*WWuPEwXkU6XZB0HoTNpfag.png" /></figure><h3><strong>Where WebSockets are Used:</strong></h3><p>WebSockets have found applications in various web development scenarios where real-time communication is crucial. Here are some common use cases:</p><ul><li><strong>Chat applications:</strong> WebSockets enable instant messaging and chat functionality, allowing users to receive and send messages in real-time.</li><li><strong>Real-time dashboards:</strong> Applications displaying live data updates, such as stock tickers or sports scores, benefit significantly from WebSockets.</li><li><strong>Collaborative editing tools:</strong> Documents or files can be edited simultaneously by multiple users, with changes reflected instantly for all participants.</li><li><strong>Multiplayer games:</strong> Real-time updates in online games, like player positions or actions, are facilitated by WebSockets.</li><li><strong>Social media feeds:</strong> Live updates on social media platforms, such as new posts or notifications, can be delivered through WebSockets.</li></ul><p>By understanding the capabilities and limitations of WebSockets, web developers can create more engaging and interactive web experiences that leverage the power of real-time communication.</p><p><strong>I’ve harnessed the power of WebSockets to create a live chat application!</strong> You can experience it in action from <a href="https://mychatapp0.azurewebsites.net/"><strong><em>here</em></strong></a>. The source code is available on GitHub for your reference and potential contributions: <a href="https://github.com/LinukaAr/LiveChat"><strong><em>Github Repo</em></strong></a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=05e5c4661faa" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>